# John "Jack" M. Chapel

in john-jack-chapel | ⊕ jackchapel.com | ✓ chapel@usc.edu

## Summary

I am an applied microeconomist with a decade of experience conducting social science research in academic and public sector settings. I enjoy collaborating with multidisciplinary teams, working on a diverse portfolio of projects, and implementing rigorous, quantitative research designs to inform program and policy improvements.

Fields of Interest: Applied Microeconomics, Health, Labor, Public Policy Citizenship: U.S.

## EDUCATION

Ph.D., Economics, University of Southern California	2019-2024
M.A., Economics, University of Southern California	2019 – 2021
B.S., Economics (with distinction), Tulane University	2011 - 2015

## Professional Experience

University of Southern California, Schaeffer Center for Health Policy &	& Economics
Postdoctoral Scholar – Research Associate	2024-
U.S. Department of Labor, Chief Evaluation Office	
Summer Fellow	2023

University of Souther	rn California, Schaenei	r Center for Health Po	licy & Economics
Recently Assistant for F	Bryan Tysinger Director	of Hoalth Policy Microsimy	ulation

Research Assistant for Bryan Tysinger, Director of Health Policy Microsimulation 2020–2023

University of Southern California, Center for Economic & Social Research

Research Assistant for Silvia H. Barcellos, Associate Professor 2022–2023

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Division for Heart Disease and Stroke Prevention

Research Fellow (ORISE), Applied Research and Evaluation Branch
2015–2019

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Office on Smoking and Health

Research Fellow (ORISE), Evaluation and Economics teams 2014

ICF International

Summer Intern, Public Health Division

Summer Intern, Public Health Division

2013

## Research

## In-Progress and Working Papers

Distant Friends with Benefits: Social Spillover Effects from Out-of-State Medicaid Expansions

The Great Migration's Impact on Southern Inequality (with Yi-Ju Hung)

Hidden Hypertension and the Labor Force Participation of Older Americans

## Peer-Reviewed Publications

Chapel JM, Currid-Halkett E, Tysinger B. The Urban-Rural Gap in Older Americans' Healthy Life Expectancy.

Journal of Rural Health. 2024;1-11.

Chapel JM, Tysinger B, Goldman DP, Rowe JW. The Forgotten Middle: Worsening health and economic trends extend to Americans with Modest Resources Nearing Retirement. *Health Affairs*. 2023;42(9):1230-1240.

- Shantharam SS, Mahalingam M, Rasool A, Reynolds JA, Bhuiya AR, Satchell TD, **Chapel JM**, Hawkins NA, Jones CD, Jacob V, Hopkins DP. Systematic Review of Patient Characteristics, Intervention Features, and Cost of Self-Measured Blood Pressure Monitoring Interventions with Support. *American Journal of Preventive Medicine*. 2022;62(2):285-298.
- MacLeod KE, Chapel JM, McCurdy M, Minaya-Junca J, Wirth D, Onwuanyi A, Lane RI. The Implementation Cost of a Safety-Net Hospital Program Addressing Social Needs in Atlanta. *Health Services Research*. 2021;56(3):474-485.
- Hawkins NA, Bhuiya A, Shantharam S, **Chapel JM**, et al. A Replicable Approach to Promoting Effective Practices: Translating Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Research. *Journal of Public Health Management and Practice*. 2020;27(2):109-116.
- Zhang D, Ritchey M, Park C, Li J, **Chapel J**, Wang G. Association Between Medicaid Coverage and Income Status on Health Care Use and Costs Among Hypertensive Adults After Enactment of the Affordable Care Act. *American Journal of Hypertension*. 2019;32(10):1030-1038.
- Chapel JM & Wang G. Understanding Cost Data Collection Tools to Improve Economic Evaluations of Health Interventions. Stroke and Vascular Neurology. 2019;4(4).
- Yarnoff B, Khavjou O, Elmi J, Lowe-Beasley K, Bradley C, Amoozegar J, Wachtmeister D, Tzeng J, **Chapel JM**, Teixeira-Poit S, The Paul Coverdell National Acute Stroke Program Team. Estimating the Costs of Implementing Components of Stroke Systems of Care and Data-Driven Quality Improvement in the Paul Coverdell National Acute Stroke Program. *Preventing Chronic Disease*. 2019;16:190061.
- Chapel JM, Ritchey MD, Zhang D, Wang G. Prevalence and Medical Costs of Chronic Diseases Among Adult Medicaid Beneficiaries. *American Journal of Preventive Medicine*. 2017;53(6 Suppl 2):S143-S154.

# PRESENTATIONS, MEDIA, AND OTHER PUBLICATIONS

## **Conferences and Invited Presentations:** (\* = coauthor, † = poster)

- 2024: Urban Institute, San Diego State University, USC Center for Economic and Social Research Seminar, Columbia Aging Center Seminar
- 2023: California State University-Long Beach Economics Seminar, USC Applied Microeconomics Seminar, ACAP Social Determinants of Health Learning Collaborative
- 2022: Aging Society Research Network Annual Meeting
- 2021: International Microsimulation Association World Congress (2)
- 2020: Academy Health Annual Research Meeting\*, Aging Society Research Network Annual Meeting\*
- 2019: American Public Health Association\*, Annual Conference on the Science of Dissemination and Implementation in Health\*, Society for Applied Anthropology Annual Meeting\*, Society for Prevention Research Annual Meeting†
- 2018: CDC Evaluation Day
- 2017: Academy Health Annual Research Meeting<sup>†</sup>, Annual Conference on the Science of Dissemination and Implementation in Health\*<sup>†</sup>, Art & Science of Health Promotion Conference\*
- 2016: QCOR\*†

#### Media:

Interviews: A Health Podyssey Podcast: Jack Chapel on Health Trends in a Shrinking Middle Class; InfoTrak:

Jack Chapel on rural life expectancy

Features: New York Times: The Income Gap Jeopardizing Retirement for Millions; U.S. News & World Report:

Nearing Retirement, America's Lower-Middle Class Faces Increasingly Bad Health

#### **Reports:** (\* = coauthored)

"Economic Evaluation: Intervention Cost Analysis in Public Health" (2018) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

- "Best Practices for Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Programs: A Guide to Effective Health Care System Interventions and Community Programs Linked to Clinical Services" (2017) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.\*
- "What Could Be Addressed in an Evidence-Informed State Workplace Health Promotion Law?" (2017) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.\*
- "The Shands Jacksonville Patient-Centered Medical Home Diabetes and Hypertension Self-Management Education Model: Program Costs Summary" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.
- "From Policy to Implementation: Collaborative Drug Therapy Management in an Independent Pharmacy" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.
- "Science-in-Brief synopsis of Do State Community Health Worker Laws Align with Best Available Evidence?" (2016)
  Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

# Honors & Awards

University of Southern California PhD Academy Scholarship and Research Fund small grant; Dornsife/graduate

school fellowship (2 years)

Centers for Disease Control CDC/ATSDR Honor Award for Excellence in Program or Policy Evaluation

(nominated with coauthors)

Tulane University Cum Laude; Dean's List; annual merit-based scholarship

## Professional Activities

Teaching: Guest Lecturer (2) for USC School of Pharmacy BPSI407: Pharmaceutical and Health Eco-

nomics, CDC DHDSP 2019 Grantee Workshop, CDC DHDSP Evaluation Coffee Break Webinars, CDC DHDSP 5-Part Webcast on the Basics of Economic Evaluation, Polygence Tutoring

Membership: American Economic Association, American Society of Health Economists

Referee Service: Health Affairs, Epidemiology, Scientific Reports, Public Health Nutrition, BMC Health Services

Research, Journal of Public Health Management and Practice, INQUIRY

## SKILLS

Software: Stata, ArcGIS, Matlab, NVivo, Microsoft Office suite (Word, Excel, Powerpoint)

Programming: Stata, R, Python, LaTex, Linux, SQL

Graduate coursework: Applied Econometrics for Program & Policy Evaluation, Big Data Econometrics, Health

Economics, Empirical Analysis of Economic Development, Urban Economics, Industrial Organization, Microeconomics, Macroeconomics, Econometrics, Probability & Statistics,

Political Economy (audit), Labor Economics (audit)